Register of the Dixy Lee Ray papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Dixy Lee Ray papers,
1937-1982
82106
Hoover Institution Archives
170 manuscript boxes, 14 oversize boxes, 3 card file boxes, 3 cubic feet boxes, 135 envelopes, 1 album box, 7 slide boxes, 16 motion picture film reels, 1 videotape cassette, 2 phonorecords, 3 linear feet of memorabilia (119.0 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches, reports, studies, printed matter, audiovisual material, and memorabilia relating primarily to nuclear energy in the United States, and to Washington state politics. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Ray, Dixy Lee
Access
Collection open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1982.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1914, September 3 Born, Tacoma, WA.
1937 B.A., Mills College, Oakland, CA.
1938 M.A., Mills College (LL.D., 1967)
1939-1942 Teacher, Oakland Public Schools and Pacific Grove Public Schools, CA.
1942-1943 John Switzer fellow, Stanford, CA.
1945 Ph.D. (Marine Biology), Stanford University
1945-1972 Associate professor of zoology, University of Washington, Seattle, WA.
1959 Author,
1960-1963 Special consultant in biological oceanography, U.S. National Science Foundation
1963-1972 Director, Pacific Science Center, Seattle
1964 Visiting professor, Stanford; Chief scientist, Research Vessel TE VEGA Expedition, International Indian Ocean
1969 Member, Presidential Task Force on Oceanography
1972 Member, Atomic Energy Commission
1972-1975(January) Chairman
1975(January-June) Assistant Secretary of State for Oceans and International Environmental and Scientific Affairs
1977-1981 Governor, State of Washington
1980, September 18 Lost her bid for reelection in state open primary
1981- Writer and lecturer
Introduction
The Dixy Lee Ray collection in the Hoover Institution Archives consists of her personal papers accumulated during the years 1937 to 1981. The materials, amounting to some hundred and eighty boxes, document principally her activities as director of the Pacific Science Center in Seattle; as member and chairman of the Atomic Energy Commission; as assistant secretary of state, and as governor of the State of Washington. Official papers stemming from her tenure as governor are kept in Olympia, as part of the Washington State Archives.
The arrangement of the collection closely follows her career path, with materials from her various offices or occupations treated chronologically in separate series.
The biographical series documents Dixy Lee Ray's personal life, including her early years as a graduate student in biology (boxes 6-7). Of special interest is her complete genealogical record (box 5).
The correspondence series is small, as it represents only those letters exchanged when Dixy Lee Ray did not hold an official position. Correspondence of 1973, for instance, is to be found in the Atomic Energy Commission series. Also filed in this correspondence series are private letters exchanged over a number of years and therefore kept together instead of being placed into different series. Of particular interest is the large folder of correspondence with Marion Reed, Dixy Lee Ray's sister, and her husband Gordon (box 9).
The speeches and writings series consists mostly of articles on the subject of nuclear energy and biological research, as well as some speeches given after she left office.
The subject file reflects Dixy Lee Ray's academic formation and professional involvement, and is generally orientated towards scientific topics. It contains a very large section on energy, particularly nuclear energy, with many reports and studies on the safety of nuclear power plants and the disposal of radioactive waste (boxes 16-25). Other folders of interest are those on the Joint Committee on Atomic Energy (box 39).
The Pacific Science Center series provides a good picture of Dixy Lee Ray's efforts to promote interest in science, particularly among young people, as evidenced by the files on the sea use program (box 54), the summer oceanography classes (box 57) and the television continuity public relations program (box 58). The minutes of the Oceanographic Commission of Washington's meetings constitute a sizeable part of this series (boxes 50-52) and readers interested in this subject should also consult the many files on oceanography in the subject file (boxes 33-34).
The Atomic Energy Commission series is probably the most valuable part of the collection, with its direct link to issues of great national and international significance. As for all the other major series, a big correspondence section is present, with important letters to heads of state and of American and foreign agencies (boxes 60-68), as well as a record of most of the speeches delivered by Dixy Lee Ray during that time (boxes 81-87). The files on her travels abroad (boxes 88-89) to attend international conferences and meet with foreign officials in charge of nuclear policy provide valuable information, as does the file on the visit to the United States of French atomic officials (box 89). On the working relationship between the Atomic Energy Commission and the executive branch, files on the Office of Management and Budget (box 78) and the White House (box 89) are to be consulted. This series also contains a very important file on the implementation of the Energy and Research Development Administration, one of the two agencies (the other being the Nuclear Regulatory Commission) created at the Atomic Energy Commission's dissolution, on ll October 1974 (box 69).
The State Department series' most specific contribution is the file on the establishment and the role of the Bureau for Oceans and International Environmental and Scientific Affairs (box 98), a newly created office which Dixy Lee Ray took over with enthusiasm but one with which she became rapidly frustrated, as indicated in particular by her correspondence (boxes 91-98).
The small interim years series consists for the most part of correspondence dealing with her numerous speaking engagements, which were scheduled by her agent, the Leigh Lecture Bureau. But Dixy Lee Ray was already thinking of running for governor: her victorious bid of 1976 for that position is recorded in the gubernatorial campaigns series, which also includes, for the sake of coherence, her unsuccessfull campaign of 1980 for re-election. Both campaign series have original files documenting general strategies, staff work, popular support; fund-raising records and statements for the Public Disclosure Commission are particularly well kept and extensive for the 1976 campaign (boxes 105-110 and 112-114).
The governorship series is the largest of the collection, with substantial files on budget conference notes (boxes 121-124), higher education (boxes 137-138), the eruption of Mount St. Helens in May of 1980 (boxes 140-142), the penitentiary system (boxes 144-145), town hall meetings (boxes 162-163), various Washington State agencies (boxes 164-169).
A considerable amount of audio-visual material complements the collection. Most noteworthy are an extensive series of photographs depicting Dixy Lee Ray in official functions, especially as director of the Atomic Energy Commission and as governor of the state of Washington, and the recordings on cassettes of virtually all of the speeches she gave while governor.
Location of Original Materials
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
U.S. Atomic Energy Commission.; Audiotapes.; Conservatism.; Moving-pictures.; Nuclear energy--United States.; Nuclear energy.; Phonorecords.; United States--Politics and government.; Video tapes.; Washington (State)--Politics and government.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1937-1981 (Boxes 1-8)
  Scope and Contents note
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1966-1981 (Boxes 9-11)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1959-1982 (Box 12)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1963-1981 (Boxes 13-44)
- PACIFIC SCIENCE CENTER, 1963-1972 (Boxes 45-58)
- ATOMIC ENERGY COMMISSION, 1972-1975 (Boxes 59-89)
- STATE DEPARTMENT, 1975 (Boxes 90-103)
- INTERIM YEARS, 1975-1976 (Box 104)
- GUBERNATORIAL CAMPAIGNS, 1976, 1980 (Boxes 105-118)
- GOVERNORSHIP, 1977-1981 (Boxes 119-169)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1937-1981 (Boxes 170-177)
- PHONOTAPE CASSETTES (Boxes 178-180)
- PERSONAL AND CONFIDENTIAL MATERIALS (Box 181)
- MEMORABILIA (Boxes 182-185)
- MOTION PICTURE FILMS
- PHONORECORDS
- VIDEOTAPE CASSETTES
- PHOTOGRAPHS
- SLIDES
- INCREMENTAL MATERIALS
- DECLASSIFIED U.S. GOVERNMENT DOCUMENTS RELEASED IN 2014
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1937-1981
  - Articles about Dixy Lee Ray (Box 1)
    - 1963-1972
    - 1972-1975
    - 1977-1981
  - Awards
  - Bank statements
  - Bank statements (Box 2-3)
  - Biographical data (Box 4)
  - Biographies, inclusion of DLR in
  - Boats
  - Business cards (of DLR and others)
  - Dogs
    - General
    - Correspondence regarding an article in the, 1975 February 2
    - Sympathy letters received upon the death of Jacques and Ghillie (2 folders)
  - Financial matters
  - Fox Island
  - Genealogical Record (2 volumes) (Box 5)
  - Graduate work in zoology and morphology at Mills College and Stanford University, 1937-1942 (Box 6)
    - Microbiology lecture notes, 1942
    - Research notes (2 folders)
    - Thesis. Handwritten first original copy (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Health
  - Honorary degrees
  - Insurance policies
  - Letters of recommendation, written by DLR (Box 8)
  - Memberships
    - Alumni associations, clubs, organizations, etc.
    - Boards and commissions
  - Miscellanea
  - Monogram
  - Motor vehicles
  - Motorhome
  - Moves
  - Taxes (2 folders)
  - Travel, 1976
  - University of Washington. See also SUBJECT FILE
    - Leave of absence
    - Research in microbiology
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1966-1981
  - General, 1981 (Box 9)
  - Carlson, Edward, 1967-1980
  - Carson, Stanley F., 1973-1980
  - Castillo, Joseph R., 1976
  - Deane, Evelyn (Executive Secretary for Mills College), 1975
  - Doub, William O., 1975
  - Green, Lora C., 1976
  - Hanna, Paul, 1976
  - Knodle, Wilma G., 1976
  - Krieg, Alden F., 1975
  - Martin, A.W., 1976-1980
  - Miller, Dorothy, 1976
  - Owen, Ray, 1967-1977
  - Raymond, Lawrence P., 1976
  - Reid, Marion and Gordon
    - n.d
    - 1967-1974
  - Scherer, Paul A., 1966-1973
  - Steele, A.R., 1973-1977
  - University of Washington, Department of Zoology, 1972-1976
  - Vest, George S., 1976
  - Woodwick, Keith, 1976
  - Birthday and Christmas cards (various years) (Box 10-11)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1959-1981
  - "The Case for Nuclear Power." Reprint by the Western Environmental Trade Association of a special series of articles that DLR prepared for, n.d (Box 12)
  - . Typewritten draft of an outline for DLR's autobiography
  - "Marine Fungi and Wood Borer Attack." Mimeographed copy of a study, 1959
  - "Miracle of Water." Printed copy of a paper presented at the symposium "Challenge for Survival 1968: Land, Air and Water for Man in Megalopolis," sponsored by The New York Botanical Garden and the Rockefeller Univer- sity, 25-26 April 1968, and published in, November 1968
  - Notes
    - Energy
    - Food and development
    - Goethe's Faust
    - Nuclear power
    - Science (Pacific Science Center years)
    - Science and government
  - "Nuclear Power: How Safe?" Photocopy of a typewritten statement answering a series of questions put to DLR while chairman of the Atomic Energy Commission
  - "Nuclear Power! In Search Of An Ombudsman." Printed copy of an article published in, July 1969
  - "Nuclear Power Should Not Be Accepted Because There Is A Crisis." Two printed copies of an article, n.d
  - Speaking invitations, 1981
  - Speech notes, 1981
  - "Water!" Printed copy and photocopy of a paper, adapted for publication, presented at the symposium "Challenge for Survival 1968," and published in, November/December 1968
  - "Water: An Account Of A Curious Liquid And What It Does." Typewritten copy and photocopy of a study
  - "Water Water Everywhere... But What If It Is Bad?" Printed copy of an article published in, March 1970
  - "Why Don't They Look It Up?" Printed copy of an article published in, April 1982
- SUBJECT FILE, 1963-1981
  - Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations (Box 13)
  - Aerospace Corporation
  - Agnew, Harold
  - Alaska
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science
  - American Institute for Public Service
  - American Society of Safety Engineers
  - American Women in Radio and Television
  - Americans for Energy Independence
  - Anderson, John B.
  - Antarctic (Box 14)
    - Salmon rearing
    - Treaty Representatives - Eighth Consultative Meeting, Oslo, Norway, 9-20 June 1975
  - Argonne National Laboratory
  - Associated Universities, Inc.
  - Association of Washington Business
  - Bagnariol, John
  - Battelle
  - Bechtel Corporation
  - Biology
  - Blue Water Educational Institute, Inc.
  - Blumenthal, Michael
  - Bonneville Power Administration
  - Bonneville Regional Advisory Council (Box 15)
  - Bosanko, Howard J.
  - Boston Museum of Science
  - Botany
  - Brookhaven National Laboratory
  - Brazil
  - Bundy, Ted
  - Butterworth, Blair
  - California State University Northridge
  - Canada - Foreign relations - United States
  - Carter, Jimmy
  - Chakravarti, Dr.
  - Challenge of the Seventies. Governor's Conference, Olympia, Washington, 30 September-1 October 1970
  - Climatic change
  - Coalition for Protective Legislation
  - Coastal Society
  - Coastal States Conference on Ocean Mining Law, Portland, Oregon, 11-13 December 1968
  - Coastal Zone Management Act Amendments of, 1976
  - Colorado - "Sunset Laws" draft
  - Columbia River Interstate Compact
  - Commission on Critical Choices for Americans (Box 16)
  - Commoner, Barry
  - Cooney, Lloyd E.
  - Council on International Economic Policy
  - Crown Zellerbach Corporation
  - Democratic National Committee, 1977-1979
  - Denenberg, Herbert
  - Desert agriculture
  - Detente - Germany
  - Development
  - DiBona, Charles J.
  - Donohue, Hubert F.
  - Economic Development Council of Puget Sound
  - Education
  - Edwards, James
  - , 1979
  - Energy. See also Brazil, Japan, Middle East, New England, Pacific Basin, Pacific Northwest, Puget Sound, Sweden, Taiwan, Washington State
    - General (3 folders)
    - General (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - Alternate sources
    - Bioenergy
    - Coal (Box 18)
    - Cogeneration
    - Conservation
    - Electricity
    - Ethanol
    - Gas. See also Alaska and Canada
    - Geothermal energy
    - Methanol
    - Nuclear energy. See also Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Studies and Silkwood, Karen
      - General (2 folders)
      - General (4 folders) (Box 19)
      - Anti-nuclear movement. See also Mead, Margaret and Nader, Ralph (Box 20)
        - General
        - California, 1976
        - Tennessee, 1974
      - Breeder reactors
        - General
        - Liquid Metal Fast Breeder Reactor (2 folders)
      - Fusion
      - Plutonium (Box 21)
      - Proliferation
      - Safeguards
      - Uranium
      - Uranium (4 folders) (Box 22)
      - Wastes (Box 23)
        - General (2 folders)
        - High-level
        - Low-level (Box 24)
          - General (2 folders)
          - National Governors' Association Task Force
        - Radioactive Waste Management Program. See also State Planning Council on Radio- active Waste Management
        - Spent nuclear fuel
        - Transportation (2 folders)
    - Oil (petroleum, gasoline). See also Alaska, Canada, Northern Tier Pipeline, and Puget Sound
      - General
      - Shales (Box 25)
      - Spills
    - Solar energy
      - General
      - Conference, Washington, D.C., 10 June 1974
    - Synthetic fuels
  - Energy Commercialization Enterprises
  - , 1976-1980
  - Energy Research and Development Administration. See also ATOMIC ENERGY COMMISSION
  - Environment (Box 26)
  - Equal Rights Amendment
  - Evans, Dan. Transcripts of press conferences
  - Evergreen State College
  - Federal Council for Science and Technology
  - Federal Emergency Management Agency
  - Federal Energy Administration Act of, 1973
  - Federal Nonnuclear Energy Research and Development Act of, 1974
  - Federal Water Quality Act of Amendments to, 1977
  - Ferguson, Adele
  - Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory
  - Fitterer, Rev. John A.
  - Fluoridation (Box 27)
  - Food problem
  - Ford, Gerald R. - Staff
  - Forestry
  - Fudenberg, H.H.
  - Garcia, Joe
  - Government
  - Government Employees Insurance Company
  - Grand Coulee Dam
  - Guzzo, Louis R.
  - Hand, Learned
  - Hanford. See also ATOMIC ENERGY COMMISSION, McCormack, Mike (Box 28)
  - Hartley, Roland T.
  - Hazardous materials, transportation of
  - Health
  - Honeywell, Inc.
  - Hopkins Marine Station. See Stanford University
  - Hospitals
  - Housing
  - Hurley, Margaret
  - Hydrodynamic Development Corporation, Inc.
  - India
  - Indians
    - General
    - Ft. Lawton Park Advisory Committee
  - Innova, Inc. See also Chakravarti, Dr.
  - Intergovernmental Personnel Act of, 1970 (Box 29)
  - Intermountain Science Experience Center
  - International Atomic Energy Agency
  - International Trade Conference, 3rd Annual, Seattle, Washington, 12 May 1977
  - International Women's Year, 1975
  - Iran
  - Japan
  - Jenkins, David
  - Journalism
  - King County, Washington - Stadium construction
  - Kissinger, Henry
  - KMS Fusion, Inc.
  - Lake Washington (Box 30)
  - Lapp, Ralph
  - Larson, Clarence
  - Lawrence Livermore Laboratory
  - Lockheed Aircraft Corporation
  - Longley, James Bernard
  - Luvera, Paul N.
  - McDermott, Jim
  - Magnuson, Jermaine
  - Magnuson, Warren
  - Maier, Cornell
  - Mallon, Robert P.
  - Marshal Aid Commemoration Commission
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology
  - Mead, Margaret
  - Metzger, H. Peter
  - Middle East. See also Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Studies
  - Miller, Mrs. Pendleton. See also University of Washington and PACIFIC SCIENCE CENTER
  - Milwaukee Railroad. See also GOVERNORSHIP, Washington State Agencies, Transportation Department
  - Miscellanea
  - Moon
  - Moynihan, Patrick
  - Mt. Hood Community College
  - Nader, Ralph. See also ATOMIC ENERGY COMMISSION, Doub, William O.
  - National Accelerator Laboratory. See Fermi (Box 31)
  - National Center for Productivity
  - National Democratic Policy Committee
  - National Energy Institute - Establishment proposal
  - National Science Foundation
  - Neurosciences
  - New England
  - Nimeh, Frances D.
  - Nisqually Delta
  - Northern Tier Pipeline
  - Northern Tier Pipeline (Box 32)
  - Nuclear Power Plant Siting Bill
  - Nuclear Regulatory Commission
  - O'Murphy, Karl O.
  - O'Neil, Eugene
  - Oak Ridge National Laboratory
    - Biological Division
    - Museum
    - Studies
    - Studies (Box 33)
  - Oceanography. See also Zoology
  - Oceanography (3 folders) (Box 34)
  - Offshore industrial-port islands
  - Olympic College
  - Organized crime
  - Pacific Basin (Box 35)
  - Pacific Northwest
  - Pacific Northwest Electric Power Planning and Conservation Act
  - Pacific Northwest Nuclear Power Plant Siting Study
  - Pacific Northwest Regional Commission
  - Pacific Northwest Regional Power Legislation
  - Pacific Northwest Sea
  - Pacific Northwest Utilities Conference Committee
  - Pacific Regional Committee - Marshall Scholarships, 1973
  - Pacific Resources, Inc.
  - Peninsula Light Company
  - Pensions
  - People's Republic of China
  - Pesticides
  - Pierce County, Washington - Agricultural Conservation Program, 1975
  - Potter, V.R.
  - President's Reorganization Project (Reorganization of Federal Emergency Preparadness and Response Programs)
  - Puget Sound
  - Puget Sound, Group Health Cooperative of
  - Puget Sound Health Plan Council (Box 36)
  - Puget Sound Hospital
  - Puget Sound Power & Light Company
  - Ray, Marguerite W.
  - Reid, Gordon
  - Reid, Marion R.
  - Rockefeller, Nelson A.
  - Saint Martin's College
  - San Juan Islands
  - Satsop Nuclear Power Plant
  - Saurs, Barbara K.
  - Scherer, Paul A.
  - Schlesinger, James A.
  - Science
    - General
    - List of talks included in "Suits: Speaking of Research" - Page proofs
      - 2-253
      - 256-458 (Box 37)
  - Seattle Chamber of Commerce
  - Seattle Engineering Department
  - , 3 April 1979
  - Seattle, Port of. See South Korea
  - Seattle Professional Engineering Employment Association
  - Silkwood, Karen
  - Simon, William E.
  - Smithkline Company
  - South Korea - Foreign Relations - Port of Seattle
  - Spellman, John
  - Spokane City Plan Commission
  - Stanford University
  - State Planning Council on Radioactive Waste Management
  - Strategic Arms Limitation Talks
  - Stratospheric ozone (Box 38)
  - Stuntz, Daniel E.
  - Sweden (2 folders)
  - Tacoma public schools
  - Taiwan
  - Taylor, Theodore B.
  - Technology
  - Teller, Edward
  - Terrorism
  - Three Mile Island
  - Trident Base (Box 39)
  - Union Carbide Corporation
  - United Nations
  - United States
    - General
    - Coast Guard
    - Congress
      - General
      - House of Representatives Committee on Foreign Affairs
      - Joint Committee on Atomic Energy. See also ATOMIC ENERGY COMMISSION, Hearings
        - General
        - Departure of Chet Holifield and Craig Hosmer
        - Membership
    - Department of the Army - Seattle District (Box 40)
    - Department of Defense
    - Department of State
    - Flag Merchant Marine
    - Foreign Relations
      - Canada. See Canada
      - Japan
    - Governors
    - Navy
  - University of Arizona
  - University of Washington
    - General
    - Arboretum Plan
    - Department of Zoology
    - Department of Zoology (Box 41)
    - Friday Harbor Laboratories
  - Vinton, W.J.
  - Washington Army and Air National Guard
  - Washington Association of Sheriffs and Police Chiefs
  - Washington Council on International Trade
  - Washington Energy Research Center
  - Washington Health Care Facilities Authority
  - Washington Oil Port
  - Washington-Oregon Potato and Onion Association
  - Washington Public Ports Association
  - Washington Public Power Supply System
  - , Spring/ Summer 1980
  - Washington State
    - Agencies. See also GOVERNORSHIP, Washington State Agencies
    - Democratic Central Committee, 1977-1978
    - Democratic Convention, 1978
    - Economy
    - Energy
    - Governors
    - Legislature (Box 42)
      - Bills (2 folders)
      - Candidates nominated for, 1980
      - Committees
        - Energy
        - Labor
        - State Capitol
        - State Government
        - Statute Law
        - Transportation - Ferry Acquisition Program
        - Ways and Means
          - Legislative Reference Notes
          - Operating and Capitol Budget Summary
      - Initiatives
      - Miscellanea
      - Resolutions
      - Roll calls
    - Maps (Box 43)
    - Toll bridges, tunnels and ferries
    - Tourism
  - Washington State Association of Group Homes
  - Washington State Developmental Disabilities Council
  - Washington State Guard
  - Washington State Interagency Committee for Outdoor Recreation
  - Washington State Labor Council